Guide to the Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh Records, 1931-2002 AIS.2000.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh Records
1931-2012
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh
AIS.2000.12
8 Linear Feet (13 boxes and one flat file)
The Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh (AAAP) was established in 1929. The purpose of AAAP is to promote the common interests of amateur astronomers while further advancing the science of astronomy through public education programs and scientific research. This collection spans the years 1931 to the present and consists of historical materials, official papers, newsletters, day books, membership information, articles and photographs. The records also include the personal papers from two prominent members of the organization.
History
The Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh, Inc. (AAAP) was established in 1929 as a non-profit corporation. The purpose of AAAP is to promote the common interests of amateur astronomers while further advancing the science of astronomy through public education programs and scientific research. Leo Scanlon and Chester Roe organized the first meeting of the AAAP in June 1929. In less than a year the organization became so well established it joined the newly created Astronomical Section of the Academy of Science and Art of Pittsburgh. In October 1929 the AAAP proposed the construction of a planetarium and ten years later the Buhl Planetarium opened to the public.
The original interest of the group focused on home built telescopes, but the success of the Buhl Planetarium broadened the vision to include public lectures and star parties. During the 1950's and 1960's the organization continued to study home built telescopes and met with other amateur groups. The group's members closely followed the emerging U.S. space program and frequently published related articles in the local newspapers.
In the mid-1970's the AAAP began exploring construction of an observatory. After various proposals, site location studies, and raising $23,000, the Wagman Observatory was dedicated in June 1987. Located in Deer Lakes Park, the observatory bears the name of the former Allegheny Observatory Director and friend of the AAAP, Nicholas E. Wagman.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection spans the years 1931 to the present and is comprised of ongoing deposits of material from the Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh. The records in the collection include historical materials, official papers, newsletters, day books, membership information, articles and photographs. The records also include personal papers from two prominent members of the organization.
The collection is arranged into 11 series. Additional notes on each series can be found in the container list at the series level. The records in some series may overlap due to the nature of continuing deposits and will be cross-referenced in the series scope notes.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh, April 20, 2000.
Additional materials were donated in November 2002, February 2003, March 2003, January 2007, and March 2013.
Previous Citation
Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh Records, 1931-2002, AIS.2000.12, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Astronomers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc. -- Archives; Societies; Nicholas E. Wagman Observatory; Amateur Astronomers Association of Pittsburgh -- Archives; Scanlon, Leo J. (Leo John); Schmidt, Robert A.
- Historical Materials, 1948-1999; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains historical material relating to the AAAP; programs and events; and biographical information about significant individuals in the association. These materials include a historical timeline, anniversary programs, memoirs, event programs, minutes, and correspondence.
  - Meeting Minutes, September 1998 - June 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "History of the AAAP," a timeline (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 50th Anniversary Program, June 9, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 60th Anniversary Program, June 11, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Thank You Letters (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Schedule for Open House, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons by Robert Schmidt (see also Series X, Box 10, folder 5) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George G. Lindbloom (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Programs and Events, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dedication Program, Valley View Observatory Historic Marker (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Leo Scanlon Memoirs and Biography, (see also Series IX, Box 9), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Astronomical League Regional Convention Program, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Membership Lists, 1931-2000; II.
  Series II consists of membership lists for the years 1931 to 2000. The member list for 1931-1939 is a bound volume and is located in Series VI, box 6, ff 2 with other bound materials.
  - 1950-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Membership Cards (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Wagman Observatory, 1985-1996; III.
  Series III pertains to the Wagman Observatory and includes blueprints, dedication programs, correspondence, registration books, and visitor logs.
  - Construction Plans, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blueprints, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dedication Program, June 13, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letter, re: uncompleted time capsule (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dedication of Brashear 11 inch refractor, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Registration Book, June 1987 - October 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Registration Book, April 1992 - March 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Guest Book, First Light of Brashear 11 inch refractor, October 7, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Visitor Logs (microfiche copies), 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Newsletters, 1948-1999; IV.
  Series IV contains the organization's newsletters from 1948 to 1999. The original newsletter, Stargazer, began in 1948 and changed to The Bulletin in 1957 then again to The Guide Star in 1967. The information in these newsletters describes local activities and discoveries of the AAAP. They also include articles by AAAP members on astronomical happenings around the world.
  - Stargazer, Vol. III, - Vol. X, 1948 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - The Bulletin, 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9-18)
  - The Guide Star, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - The Guide Star, Vol. 14 - Vol. 33, 1980 1999 (Box 4, Folder 1-21)
  - The Guide Star, Vol. 34 - Vol. 46, 2000-2012 (Box 4a, Folder 1-13)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1954-1997; V.
  Series V consists of newspaper articles from 1954 to 1997. A chronological list of the majority of the clippings can be found in folder 1. The clippings are arranged by subject within the series.
  - Chronological Index of Clippings, 1954-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AAAP - general, 1955-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Amateur Astronomers - general, 1955-1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Brashear 11 inch refractor (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Light Pollution, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Public Information (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Space Flights, 1983-1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Star Parties, 1962-1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
  - Articles saved by Leo Scanlon (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Bound Volumes, 1931-1997; VI.
  Series VI contains the bound volumes in the collection. These include a membership book, account book, and day books. The day books record visitors, events, and daily observations dating from 1931 to 1938. Other volumes include Popular Astronomy journals kept by AAAP members for the years 1932 through 1937. In addition, the Star Atlas and Reference Handbook that was kept at the Valley View Obsevatory in the North Side of Pittsburgh can be found in this series. This volume was published in 1927 and includes annotations by Leo Scanlon.
  - Account Book, 1945-1983 (Box 6, Volume 1)
  - Membership Book, 1931-1939 (Box 6, Volume 2)
  - Day Book, 1931 (Box 6, Volume 3)
  - Day Book, 1932 (Box 6, Volume 4)
  - Day Book, 1933 (Box 6, Volume 5)
  - Day Book, 1934 (Box 6, Volume 6)
  - Day Book, 1935 (Box 6, Volume 7)
  - Day Book, 1936 (Box 6, Volume 8)
  - Day Book, 1937 (Box 6, Volume 9)
  - Day Book, 1938 (Box 6, Volume 10)
  - Popular Astronomy, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Volume 11)
  - Popular Astronomy, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Volume 12)
  - Popular Astronomy, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Volume 13)
  - Amateur Telescope Making, Scientific American, 1937 (Box 6, Volume 14)
  - Star Atlas and Reference Handbook, by Arthur P. Norton, Gail and Inglis, London, England, 1927 (Box 6, Volume 15)
- Photographs, VII.
  Series VII contains photographs of group members and activities for the years 1931 through 1999. Approximately 180 images in black and white or color in various sizes are collected in this series. This series is housed separately in the Media room at the Archives Service Center.
  - Photographs, 1931-1999 (Box 7)
- Official Papers, 1941-2002; VIII.
  Series VIII contains official papers of the AAAP. The majority of the material is AAAP meeting minutes and The Guide Star newsletter for the years 1998-2002. These materials can be found in the recording secretary file from July 2001 to September 2002 along with the secretary's correspondence, agendas, and membership directory. Information in this series also pertains to the controversial issue of changing the monthly meeting dates in 2001. Other materials include correspondence, insurance policies, and membership lists. In addition, this series contains the Constitution and By-laws of the AAAP that were amended as of March 14, 1997.
  - Constitution and By-laws, March 14, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, September 1997 - May 2000 September 2000 - May 2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Recording Secretary File, July 2001 - January 2002 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Recording Secretary File, February 2002 - September 2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - AAAP Member Survey regarding monthly meeting dates, October 2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Astronomical League Bulletin, May 1951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers, Insurance Policies and Correspondence regarding the use of Allegheny Observatory by Amateurs, 1956-1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Membership Lists, (intermittent), 1943-1999 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Clippings, and Announcements, 1941-2001 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes (2 disks, 1 cd-rom), 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Attendance, November 2012 - April 2015 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Papers and Diaries of Leo Scanlon, 1929-1949; IX.
  Series IX consists of the private papers and diaries of AAAP co-founder Leo Scanlon. Scanlon co-founded the AAAP with Chester Roe in 1929 and remained an active member for 70 years until his death in 1999. Scanlon was an accomplished telescope maker and observer which is reflected in his papers. The astronomical community regarded Scanlon highly as a person and as an emissary of popular science, particularly astronomy. Leo Scanlon's memoirs and biography can be found in this collection under Series I, Historical Materials, located in Box 1, folder 12.
  The bulk of the material in this series is the eleven diaries kept by Scanlon from 1929 to 1937. The diaries include correspondence, photographs, clippings, observation logs, newsletters, AAAP meeting minutes, and AAAP memorabilia. An inventory of topics and materials contained in the diaries is available for most of the volumes and can be found with the diary. The original copy of Volume 2 was donated to the Astrology Museum in Springfield, VT and is accessible in this collection as a photocopy.
  The series also consists of lecture notes, published articles, radio scripts and photographs by Leo Scanlon. Additional materials collected by Leo Scanlon include articles and photographs on telescopes, amateur astronomers, observatories and astronomical interests.
  - Bound Diaries, 1929-1937; 1.
    - Volume 1, September 1929-August 1930 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Volume 2, (photocopy), August 1930-December 1930 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Volume 3, January 1931-December 1931 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Volume 4, January 1932-June 1932 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Volume 5, (eclipse edition), July 1932-September 1932 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Volume 6, September 1932-December 1932 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Volume 7, January 1933-June 1933 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Volume 8, July 1933-December 1933 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Volume 9, January 1934-November 1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Volume 10, September 1934-July 1935 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Volume 11, Springfield Trip (Convention of Amateur Telescope Makers), 1937 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Research Papers, 2.
    - Variable Star Observer Questionnaire, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Halley's Comet, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Valley View Observatory Stationary (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - News Clippings from Pittsburgh Papers Detailing Early Space Exploration, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Lecture Notes on Telescope Setting Circles, February 1948 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Lecture Notes, 1933-1948 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Academy of Science and Art, Lecture Programs, (intermittant), 1933-1977 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Framed Letter to Mr. Scanlon from the Secretary of Smithsonian Institution, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Articles and Notes on What Amateur Astronomers thought of Astrology, 1933-1940 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Pittsburgh Moonwatch Program; Invoices and correspondence with Kaufmans in regard to financing the station, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Kiwanis Club, certificate and lecture notes, 1940-1963 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Lecture Notes on AAVSO and Telescopes, 1942-1948 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - The Science Counselor, Vol. XI, no. 1, September 1948; Article on page 83 details the construction of Cliff Raible's working model of the 200 inch Palomar Telescope. Raible was a member of the AAAP and student of John A. Brashear. The folder includes a black and white print of the model telescope. (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Sky and Telescope, Vol. I, no. 4, February 1942; Article on page 18 is about Leo Scanlon written by AAAP member Fred Garland. (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Sky and Telescope, Vol. VII, no. 1, November 1947; Article on page 3 is by Leo Scanlon on the Cliff Raible telescope model. (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - The Bulletin Index, December 3, 1936; Article on page 20 about the AAAP. (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Russell Porter File, 1946; Includes script for lecture given on astronomer and polar explorer, Russell Porter, given by Leo Scanlon on December 13, 1946; notice in Sky and Telescope magazine, article in same, and related correspondence with editor; and draft article by Scanlon for Atlantic Monthly about Russell Porter's influence on amateur astronomer groups, especially the Pittsburgh chapter. (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Script for Radio Series, "You and the Universe", written by Leo Scanlon (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, 1930-1940; Includes: Valley View Observatory (1930), Meteor Crater (1932), Autographed Photo of Rod La Roque (1934), Group Portrait of Identified Amateur Astronomers (1935), Visit to Allegheny College (1937), Group Photo at the AAVSO Convention with some identifications (1940), Moon by Vic Maier and dedicated to Leo Scanlon (1940), and J.L. Wagoner's Telescope. (Box 9, Folder 30)
- Papers and Photographs of Robert A. Schmidt, 1949-2002; X.
  Series X consists of the personal papers and photographs of Robert A. Schmidt, a member of AAAP since the 1950's. R.A. Schimdt was particularly interested in telescope making, which is strongly reflected in the materials of this series. Schmidt was also known for his astronomical cartoons that appeared in many publications over the years and are gathered together in folder 5 of this series. Other areas of interest that are represented in this series are astronomical theories and programs that the AAAP were involved in such as the Moonwatch program, an early, national satellite tracking program. Observations from the roof of Allegheny Observatory, official papers, photographs and clippings relating to the Moonwatch program can be found in folder 7.
  This series is rich with photographs and published articles both by R.A. Schmidt and others. Most of the articles appeared in club newsletters of the AAAP and the Oklahoma City Astronomer's Club. Other materials include correspondence, clippings, and biographical information on other amateur astronomers.
  R.A. Schmidt's collection of slides are housed separately in the media room.
  - Telescopes by R. A. Schimdt, 1949-1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Leo Enie's Lunar Theories, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Personal Memorabilia, Clippings, Newsletters and Photographs, 1958-2002 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Published Articles on Telescope Making by R. A. Schmidt, 1964-1999 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Astronomical Cartoons by R. A. Schmidt, (See also: Box 1, ff 8), 1976-1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mogey Refractor Memoirs, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - AAA Moonwatch Program, 1957-1962 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Yolo Schiefsspiegler Telescope, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Astronomical Occurrences and Equipment by E. Ken Owen and Howard F. Zeh, 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Equipment Made or Owned by R. A. Schimdt, 1957-1977 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Oscar Knabb File, 1968-1995 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    General Note
    Includes: correspondence, photographs, articles, clippings, and drawing of telescope.
- Secretaries Records, 1988-1996; XI.
  The Secretaries records consist of astronomy club surveys, incoming and outgoing correspondence, press releases, and records of donations to the Nicholas E. Wagman Observatory during the time that John Holtz held the office.
  - Astronomy Club Surveys, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (incoming), 1988-1995 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (outgoing), 1988-1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1992-1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Wagmen Observatory Donations, 1988-1996 (Box 11, Folder 5)